<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached some years since, by Augustin Medcalf, deceased. Master of Art, prebend of Chichester, and minister of Berwick in Sussex</title>
            <author>Medcalf, Augustine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1583D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896663</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896663</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135180</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135180)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2431:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached some years since, by Augustin Medcalf, deceased. Master of Art, prebend of Chichester, and minister of Berwick in Sussex</title>
                  <author>Medcalf, Augustine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: "A sermon on Phil. IV. 4."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians IV, 4 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135180:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135180:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Some Years ſince, BY <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STIN MEDCALF,</hi> DECEASED. Maſter of Art, Prebend of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> and Miniſter of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135180:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135180:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PHIL. IV. 4.</bibl>
                  <p>Rejoice in the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways: and again, I ſay rejoyce.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Text preſents us not only with the duty, but the incomparable priviledg of every faithful, obedient Chriſtian, who is here enjoined a ſervice ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, pleaſing, and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous, that as no man in the world beſides can have half the reaſon to do it at all; ſo every good<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135180:3"/>Chriſtian hath all the reaſon in the world to perform it always.</p>
            <p>To be pleaſed and ſatisfied, to be merry and joyful, one would think were a ſervice ſo natural and delightful to all the world, that the very commanding of it would appear one of the vaineſt and moſt needleſs injunctions ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; and to do all this upon the juſteſt ſcore, and upon a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-failing account; to entertain and accept, preſerve and always keep in ones poſſeſſion an inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Fountain of joy, ſuch as will ſupply all our wants, ſerve all our neceſſities, gratifie and pleaſe us in all conditions; to place this joy of ours in God, in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore: To command a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to do this, one would fancy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135180:3"/>(at firſt hearing it) were a very ſuperfluous Precept; it looks all one as if a man ſhould be deſired not to be a ſtock, or ſtone, or ſwine; for if he were but a man, much leſs a Chriſtian man, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but do it of his own accord, without commands or entreaties: And yet Heaven knows, ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate creatures are we grown, that God is fain to oblige us to that by poſitive expreſs command which (did we behave our ſelves in the leaſt like Chriſtian people) we could not but perform by a meer inclination of nature. Nay, did but a man obſerve the general dejectedneſs, ſullenneſs, murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and repinings that are to be met with in the converſation of moſt Chriſtians, againſt the deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and diſpoſings of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 'twould let us ſee ſufficient
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135180:4"/>reaſon why St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould in this very Epiſtle ſo often inculcate and impreſs this one duty. He thought it not enough to ſay, <hi>My brethren, rejoyce in the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 3.1.</note> but as if people were apt to forget nothing more than what they ſhould and cannot (when they truly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) but delight in moſt, he repeats his Injunction in the words of the Text,
<hi>Rejoyce in the Lord always:</hi> Nay, as if this bare repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition were not ſufficient, but that people would ſill perſiſt to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it, though they both know it, and remember it too, he does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double and impreſs it over again, hereby intimating it to be a duty of that concern, that it can never be too much repeated, becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the inſiſting upon it, 'tis every where amongſt all ſorts of perſons too little practiſed; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135180:4"/>therefore ſays he in the next words, <hi>and again I ſay, Rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to rejoyce in God always, is evermore to have a heart and mind ſo diſpoſed and ordered, that it can in an humble waiting, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant depending, and faithful ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, derive and continue to its ſelf an inexpreſſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſatisfaction, and delight, from this one conſideration , that the Lord is her God; this ſecures, that in all conditions whatſoever, ſhe is certainly under the protection of his Providence, and the care of his love, and in the arms of his mercy. And this happy aſſurance does beget and break open ſuch a fountain of joy in the ſoul, as does never, or at leaſt never need leave ſtreaming, until it empty it ſelf into thoſe Rivers of joy that are at Gods right hand; for we ſhall<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135180:5"/>find that the conſideration of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lord for his God, does furniſh the obedient humble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (for of ſuch only I would have this whole Diſcourſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) with two ſuch migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty arguments of joy, that the due weighing of them cannot chuſe but make him in all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to rejoice in this Lord, yea and again I ſay to rejoice.
<list>
                  <item>1. The obedient good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may very juſtly rejoice in God always, becauſe he is ſecure; the Lord will ſo order and govern the concernments of this temporal life as ſhall be moſt for his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and advantage.</item>
                  <item>2. He may again rejoice in the fame God, and that always too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is ſecured by him that he ſhall be prepared for and hereafter put in poſſeſſion of a better, even<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135180:5"/>a heavenly life with himfelf in his glorious Kingdom.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The obedient good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may very juſtly rejoice in God always, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the performance of this he hath the expreſs promiſe of the God of mercy and truth, with whom is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> having laid down this as a Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of unqueſtionable truth, <hi>We know that all things work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good to them that love God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom.
8.28</note> He triumphantly proceeds to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That none of the miſeries of this inferior world can do us the leaſt hurt, becauſe they cannot ſeparate us from the protection of Gods Providence, nor the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſals of his mercy, and the over-ruling beneficialneſs of his love:
<hi>'Tis not,</hi> ſays he,<note place="margin">Verſ. 35.</note>
               <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, or diſtreſs, or perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135180:6"/>or famine, or nakedneſs, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, or ſword, that ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none of theſe can hinder his mercy from doing us good, in and by our afflictions. <hi>Nay</hi> (ſays he<note place="margin">Verſ. 37.</note>) <hi>in all theſe things we are more than conquerours through him that loved us.</hi> There are few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but will readily grant men may juſtly rejoice in God when the world ſmiles upon them, and their contrivances are ſeconded with ſucceſs; ſo that by this means they proſper in the world, have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in poſſeſſion, flouriſh like a green bay-tree, and do even what they liſt; who is he ſo wretched but hath gladneſs in his heart in the time that his corn, and wine, and oyl increaſes? when their oxen are ſtrong to labour, when their barns are full of corn, when there<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135180:6"/>is no leading into captivity, no want nor complaining in their houſes, when their ſheep bring forth thouſands, and ten thouſands in their ſtreets, then men can be content to thank God for his goodneſs, and rejoice in him for the great bounty he beſtows upon the children of men. But if this very God ſhould by his wiſe and gracious Providence change the ſcene of their affairs, give their fruits to the caterpiller, and their labour to the graſhopper, blaſt the work of their hands, ſtrike their flocks with hot thunder-bolts, and bring an evil diſeaſe amongſt their herds; ſhould he make them poor in their eſtates, ſick in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, unproſperous in their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, forſaken of their friends, and a reproach and deriſion to them that are round about them,<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135180:7"/>how ready would they then be to forget the joy of their heart, and the rock of their Salvation, and think themſelves ſufficiently excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and juſtified too, if they now murmur, repine, and are angry at the dealings of Heaven; And in the height of their diſcontent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation not only quarrel with, but ſome of them curſe God to his face: This men are naturally or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the more apt to do upon this great miſtake, becauſe they believe God then only loves and does them good when he proſpers them in their temporal concerns; and that when he ſtretches out his hand and blaſts their expectation in thoſe particulars, he then only hates them, and does them miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; but how groſs an error this is, that proſperity ſhould be an infallible ſign of Gods love, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135180:7"/>adverſity of his hatred, will in a good degree appear hereafter. Nay I hope 'twill be made out, that as few men do truly rejoice in God in either condition, ſo none but the obedient, humble Chriſtian, hath the higheſt inducements to rejoice in God in both conditions, yea and again I ſay to rejoice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis the obedient humble Chriſtian who hath the trueſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to rejoice in God in the time of proſperity, and that upon this account, becauſe he is well aſſured, ſo long as he continues his faithful ſervice to God, he will bleſs his fortune, and make his proſperity do him good. But moſt people will be ready to reply, This ſeems to make a queſtion of what is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally taken for granted; whoever doubted Gods bleſſing to go along with a great Eſtate? for proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135180:8"/>(ſay they) is that, and every thing elſe that is deſirable. Did ever a large Fortune do any man hurt? who was ever the worſe for wearing ſoft clothing? for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring deliciouſly every day? for lying at eaſe, taking his pleaſure, and commanding round about him? Alas! ſenſual ſottiſh Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that we are! that can think a Swine happy becauſe ſhe hath her Trough full of waſh, which ſhe ſwills up greedily, and grunts over for joy, and having fill'd her belly, lies down and ſnorts without care or thought for the next days pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. But if we will give our ſelves the leiſure to hearken to Gods inſtruction, we ſhall find our ſelves taught by the Wiſdom from above, that 'tis not the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Temporal affluence without true Godlineſs can make any man
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135180:8"/>happy; if a man be wicked, though he be never ſo rich, he's but in the 'worſe condition for his wealth; ſuch <hi>a mans riches are kept for the owner to his hurt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.13.</note> And therefore when the Prophet
<hi>Jeremiah</hi> undertook to argue with God concerning his Judgments,
<hi>viz.</hi> Wherefore the way of the wicked proſpered? And wherefore all they were temporally happy that dealt very treacherouſly? In the concluſion of the debate he makes this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,<note place="margin">Jer.
12.1,2,3.</note> 
               <hi>Though thou haſt planted them, ſo that they have taken root, grow and bring forth fruit, yet thou O Lord, ſhalt pull them out like ſheep for the ſlaughter, for thou doſt prepare them for the day of ſlaughter.</hi> Intimating hereby, that all the good thing of this world which God ſometimes ſo liberally heaps<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135180:9"/>upon wicked men, is intended as no greater a kindneſs to them than the variety of freſh Paſture, and plenty of the pureſt Hay, is deſigned by the Graſier upon one of his fatting Bullocks; which he does not beſtow upon him only that the beaſt may grow fat and ſhine, and wallow in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his eaſe, and the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his Provinder, but only that he may the more certainly and quickly become fit ware for the market and the ſhambles. And therefore how much ſoever wicked men may think themſelves behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to any man that wiſhes them proſperity, yet when they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it better, perhaps they may ſee good cauſe to give them little thanks for ſo miſchievous an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation (rather than a Prayer); for 'tis all one as if in other words
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135180:9"/>he prayed to God to take ſuch a courſe with them as ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ruin them. So ſays <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.32.</note> 
               <hi>The turning away</hi> (or the eaſe, as
'tis in the Margent) <hi>of the ſimple ſhall ſlay them, and the proſperity of fools ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> As if there were no more certain way only to undo and irrecoverably to ruin wicked men (for ſuch are meant by fools and ſimple in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Solomon,</hi> than the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of proſperity, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to live according to their own hearts, luſts. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſo many and great are the temptations which a proſperous condition does bring along with it, that none but a very good man can uſe it with any tollerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency. Let but <hi>Nabal</hi> live in eaſe and plenty, and the wicked fool preſently tarns a Drunkard,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135180:10"/>and a Churl; for though himſelf kept a feaſt in his houſe like the feaſt of a King, and his heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him was merry and drunk, yet would he not part with one mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to <hi>David</hi> and his Soldiers who had preſerved him and his in the Wilderneſs.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.10,36.</note> So alſo that wretched rich man in our Saviours Parable, when he grew ſo wealthy that he was fain to pull down his Barns, and build greater, becauſe he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted room to lay his fruits; when he had thus done, the next thing he ſets about was to reſolve upon a life of eaſe and ſenſuality, for ſo he beſpeaks his Soul (hugging himſelf in the enjoyment of his beloved Goods), <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry, for thou haſt goods laid up for many years.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.18,19.</note> Nor was the caſe otherwiſe with Gods own people of old:<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135180:10"/>
               <note place="margin">Deut.
32.15.</note>
               <hi>When Jeſurun waxed fat, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fell a kicking againſt Heaven, and quite forgot the God that made him, and lightly eſteemed the rock of his Salvation.</hi> And we are told concerning the ſame <hi>Iſrael</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place,<note place="margin">Pſal.
78.24,30.</note> that when God rained Manna upon his people, and gave them all that they deſired, then they were not eſtranged from their luſts. And becauſe 'tis ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural for a man to be tranſported with proſperity, for this reaſon <hi>Moſes</hi> could not admit his people to the delights of <hi>Canaan</hi> before he had given them this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caveat to warn them againſt the poyſonous inſinuations of that plentiful and delightful place:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.10,11,12.</note> 
               <hi>When the Lord thy God ſhall have brought thee into the land, to give thee great and goodly cities, and houſes full of all good, things, then<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135180:11"/>beware that thou forget not the Lord who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, and out of the houſe of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</hi> And as if this one Caution were not ſufficient, he doubles it,<note place="margin">Chap. 8. from <hi>v.</hi> 10, to <hi>v.</hi>
18.</note> 
               <hi>When thou haſt eaten and art full, and haſt built goodly houſes and dwelt therein, then beware leſt thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God who brought thee out of the houſe of bondage, and ſay in thy heart, My power and the might of my hand hath gotten me this wealth: But thou ſhalt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord thy God, for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth.</hi> By all which 'tis very eaſie to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect how prone the heart of man is to abuſe the riches and good things of this world to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that God who graciouſly beſtowed them upon him; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of returning him the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135180:11"/>of praiſe and thankſgiving who hath bleſſed their endeavours in the getting all they have, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thoſe wicked men in the Prophet <hi>Habbakkuk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>In ſacrificing to their net, and burning incenſe to their drag, becauſe by them their portion is fat, and their meat plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> Nay the man after Gods own heart, holy <hi>David</hi> himſelf, began to boaſt of himſelf, and ſay in his proſperity he ſhould never be moved;<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.</note> when yet 'twas this very proſperity which betrayed him to thoſe two reproaches of his Piety, <hi>viz.</hi> the murder of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and the adultery of
<hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba;</hi> for ſo the Text tells us,<note place="margin">2 Sam.
11.1,2.</note> when his Armies were victorious abroad, and himſelf lived in plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and eaſe at home, then was the time he was tempted, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of theſe very Sins. And<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135180:12"/>indeed
<hi>Agurs</hi> Prayer will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inſtruct us,<note place="margin">Prov. 38.9.</note> how much more dangerous a proſperous condition is than an adverſe one; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how much reaſon we have to petition God to deliver us from the Sins which the one tempts us to as well as the other. Poverty indeed, he tells us, does naturally tempt men to ſteal; but riches, he aſſures us, invite and incline men to the commiſſion of a ſin of a much higher nature, even down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Atheiſm; for when once men are full, they are then in the likelieſt condition to deny God, and ſay, who is the Lord? So that upon the whole, ſince Proſperity is attended with ſuch manifold danger, and ſuch variety of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, then certainly no man hath equal reaſon to prize and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in it, that the humble
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135180:12"/>obedient Chriſtian hath; for he it is that hath the greateſt ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it ſhall do him the leaſt hurt. He hath not only a gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from the mouth of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, that the comforts of this life ſhall be added to him, (if the Allwiſe God ſees they'l do him good) upon his ſeeking firſt of all, and moſt of all, the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">Mat.
6.33.</note> But he is ſecured (that if God vouchſafes to beſtow the good things of this life upon him) he ſhall (upon his humble walking with God, and meek behaviour towards men) have Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing go along with him in the enjoyment of them.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.5.</note> And this is that that gives a value to them, and makes them good things indeed. Proſperity in fects wicked men with ſuch a ruſt and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135180:13"/>that eats into their ſoul as a canker does into their fleſh: But all this is a good man preſerved from, by vertue of Chriſts Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (one end whereof was that he might deliver us from this preſent evil world,)<note place="margin">Gal. 1.4.</note> and the prevalency of his Saviours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, who ſtill continues to petition God his Father to keep all his obedient ſervants from the evil of this world.<note place="margin">Joh.
17.15.</note> He hath Gods Spirit going along with him to lead him into the ways of Truth, Piety, and Peace; he hath the graces thereof to aſſiſt him in the ſubduing his corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and enabling him to reſiſt temptations. Nay, he hath no leſs than the Almighty God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth to ſtabliſh, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and ſettle him.<note place="margin">1 Pet.
5.16.</note> This God is his Sun to chear and comfort him;<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135180:13"/>his ſhield to defend and protect him; one who hath promiſed to withhold no good thing from them that walk uprightly, and lead a godly life.<note place="margin">Pſ. 84.11.</note> And hereby we may collect whether we have Gods bleſſing in our proſperity, when our riches don't make us a jot the more proud, or the leſs devout; ſo that we are neither high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor truſt in uncertain riches, but in the living God. Nay more, when we practiſe the advice of the Son of <hi>Syrach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3.18.</note> And the greater we are, can humble our ſelves ſo much the more, when we can find our ſelves more fervent in Prayers, and more frequent in Alms-deeds, and more obedient to all Gods Commandments; when we can obſerve our ſelves endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to be rich in good works as well as in money; being ready<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135180:14"/>to diſtribute, and willing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the diſtreſſes of our poor brethren; keeping our ſelves unſpotted from the world, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to the poor and needy; when we are thus laying up in ſtore for our ſelves a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation againſt the time to come, that we may lay hold on eternal life; when we thus make our ſelves friends of the unrighteous Mammon; putting our money out to uſury in Gods bank; lending to the Lord by giving to his poor; hoping for nothing again but his gracious acceptance here, and his merciful reward hereafter: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever finds his heart thus wrought upon by proſperity, he may well conclude he hath the bleſſing of Gods right hand as well as his left; that he hath Gods favour and love as well as his bounty and benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135180:14"/>and this is that that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters life, comfort, and ſweetneſs to all his poſſeſſions, and makes them deſirable enjoyments; ſuch a man as this may not only juſtly be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to uſe the Prayer of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.25.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, I beſeech thee ſend me now proſperity;</hi> and that becauſe he hath Gods bleſſing going along with him in it, and is made the better by it, and makes other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the better for it. But when God is pleas'd to vouchſafe it him, may in that day according to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Be joyful.</hi> Nay in the language of
<hi>David,</hi> he may ſhout for joy and be glad, and may continually ſay, Let the Lord be magnified, who is pleaſed not only to grant me proſperity, but moreover, which is the crowning joy of all, hath pleaſure in the poſterity of his ſervant:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 35.27.</note>
               <hi>For this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135180:15"/>cauſe ſhall my tongue ſpeak of his righteouſneſs, and of his praiſe all the day long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The obedient humble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath juſt reaſon to rejoice in God in time of Affliction: For being well ſatisfied that Affliction cometh not forth of the duſt, nor troubles ſpring out of the ground, but that man is born unto trouble (is appointed thereunto by the God that made him) as the ſparks fly upwards. Therefore in ſuch a time doth he (with comfort) ſeek unto God, and (with content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) doth he commit his cauſe unto him, to uſe the words of <hi>Eliphaz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job
5.6,7,8.</note> He is not now to learn that all the miſeries of this life come from an higher hand than created weakneſs is able to grapple with or controul; and therefore knowing it to be the Lords doing,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135180:15"/>he preſently lifts his eyes unto Heaven from whence cometh his help, caſting his burden upon the Lord, (who firſt laid it upon his back) who alſo hath promiſed to ſuſtain him, whileſt he doth with faith, patience and chearfulneſs ſet his ſhoulders to the bearing it; and who hath expreſly ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſ. 55.22.</note> 
               <hi>That he will never ſuffer the righteous to he moved.</hi> He looks upon Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a meſſenger ſent from God, and thereupon receives it joyfully, hearkens to it attentively, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys it with all ſubmiſſion. For he is well aſſured that our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father (unlike to our fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents) chaſtens not his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as they ſometimes do, for his pleaſure, but altogether for their profit; and he does it for this bleſſed end, that they may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his Holineſs.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.10</note> Every one<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135180:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Gods rods hath a voice as well as a laſh, and was ſent to inſtruct as well as to correct the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant. So that when once God lays his rod upon the back of an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedient Soul, he preſently anſwers the call of Gods chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Speak Lord, for thy ſervant hears. Strike on, Father, for thy child attends. O Lord, my heart is fixed, my heart is fixed. I will ſing and give praiſe, I will thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receive thy corrections, and am ſteadfaſtly purpoſed to obey thy righteous judgments: 'tis true indeed, that no chaſtening for the preſent ſeems to be joyous but grievous; nevertheleſs afterwards it yields the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs to them that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed thereby.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> 'Tis the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the bleſſed fruits that affliction brings along with it, and<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135180:16"/>ſprings out of it that makes a good man rejoice in tribulation, and heartily thank God for his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; he ſees how uſeful it is to reclaim him from ſome ſin he was too much addicted to; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigate him to the practiſe of ſome duties he was too forgetful of, or negligent in: So that upon the ſurvey of the ſpiritual benefit he receives by it, he cannot but expreſs himſelf in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of holy <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.67.</note> 
               <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray, but now</hi> (ſince I was afflicted) <hi>have I kept thy word.</hi> I now am able to ſay by my own experience (upon the obſerving the happy reformation of my naughty life) <hi>that 'tis good for me that I have been afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe thereby have I learned thy ſtatutes.</hi> And therefore, O Lord, ſince thou haſt dealt ſo well<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135180:17"/>with thy ſervant in this ſeaſonable afflicting of me, continue, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, ſuch thy loving-kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto me according to thy word.<note place="margin">Verſ.
65.</note> And indeed God hath paſs'd his word that he will in much mercy to their ſouls afflict his dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſervants in their Bodies and Eſtates, in all the concernments I mean of this temporal life, that his Wiſdom ſees will do them moſt good. And ſhould he not do ſo, he would fail in two main Articles of his Divinity (which are the great ſupporters and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his moſt beloved Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens obedience) and that is his truth and his love towards them. Thus <hi>David</hi> acquaints us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 199.75.</note> 
               <hi>I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are rights and thou in thy faithfulneſs haſt afflicted me.</hi> Intimating, that if God had not afflicted him, he<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135180:17"/>would have forfeited his Juſtice and Veracity by ſo doing; nor would his love be leſs queſtionable than his truth, if he ſhould utterly leave off correcting his deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. For this is that the Writer to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> lays down as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of everlaſting verity:<note place="margin">Heb.
12.6.</note> 
               <hi>Whom the Lord loves he chaſtens, and ſcourges every Son whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives.</hi> God, indeed, the Apoſtle tells us, expreſſes his Fatherly love in correcting of his Children, by inſtructing, chiding, and ſcourging of them, for ſo the Original doth ſignifie. And leſt we ſhould think that affliction alone is enough to intitle us to the relation of Gods Children, or ſhould argue with our ſelves, becauſe God ſcourges every ſon which he receives, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one whom he ſcourges, he receives for his ſon; The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135180:18"/>to rectifie this miſtake, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us, that though indeed 'tis true that our being without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement (whereof all are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers would) certainly evince us to be Baſtards and not Sons: Yet our bare having chaſtiſement, is not ſufficient to conclude us to be Sons and not Baſtards. For ſays he,<note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>If ye endure</hi> (not barely if you have chaſtening), <hi>God deals with you, &amp;c.</hi> if ye endure, if you humbly receive, patiently bear, thankfully employ, and fruitfully improve Gods word, and Gods rod, Gods chidings, and Gods ſcourgings to your own amendment; if they yield the peaceable fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in a conversation of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, then you may reaſonably conclude your ſelves to be Gods children: And for being ſo related, and in this ſort afflicted, whereby
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135180:18"/>that relation is ſo clearly diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you have good cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice with joy unſpeakable and glorious. How are men tranſported, and with what exuberances of exultation do they ordinarily entertain an adoption into <hi>Caeſars</hi> Family, which puts them in hopes they ſhall one day ſway a Scepter, and govern and triumph over the Kingdoms of the Earth? And yet what a trivial petit Preferment is this, if it be but compared to that inexpreſſible advancement, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received into the number of Gods Children, and admitted to be an heir and a co-heir with the Eternal Son of his love, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords! And then how much more reaſon have they not only more exceedingly to rejoice, but themſelves to be<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135180:19"/>turned as
'twere who have the ſureſt evidence of the King of Heavens love and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; who are able as 'twere to produce his gracious Letters-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents under his broad Authentick Seal of Affliction, and to ſhew in their Bodies and Eſtates theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable marks of their Heavenly Fathers love! They who find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thus ſealed to the day of Redemption, can't chuſe certainly but keep a perpetual Jubilee all their lives long, and in the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing exultation of their ſouls amidſt all their croſſes and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, muſt needs lift up their heads with joy and thankſgiving to that God who hath vouchſafed them one of the moſt certain and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſigns of his love and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, whileſt he hath been graciouſly pleaſed to exerciſe<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135180:19"/>them with affliction; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but to compleat and crown his mercy and loving-kindneſs to them, hath moreover given them patience to bear, courage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, conſtancy to perſevere, and wiſdom to improve all the croſſes he lays upon them, to his honour and their own comfort; ſo that methinks if ever a man could be allowed to be a competent Judg of his own felicity, he hath the ſureſt grounds to conclude and pronounce himſelf a happy man, when the world poſſibly thinks him poor, and miſerable, and the moſt wretched perſon, piteous up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. See the man whom <hi>Eliphaz</hi> brings in with a note of admiration, as if he had a mind to pick out and ſhew you that particular perſon whom all the world ſo much court and admire,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135180:20"/>and endeavour to make themſelves like, <hi>Behold the happy man,</hi> ſays he!<note place="margin">Job 5.17.</note> Behold him, will moſt people ſay; but alas! where ſhall we ever ſee him; a happy man indeed were a ſight worth our beholding, we ſhould never think our eyes bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter imployed than in viewing and admiring ſo rare an object: why ſays he, I'le ſhew you the man whom you ſo mightily long to ſee and glut your eyes, and bleſs your ſelves upon, your ſurveying a man whoſe condition is altogether bleſſed and deſirable: Behold him therefore whoſe Eſtate the wicked envy, the good admire, all men hope for, and the beſt only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy. Would you now, in a word know who this man is? <hi>Behold, happy is the man</hi> (ſays <hi>Eliphaz</hi>) <hi>whom God correcteth.</hi> See how moſt people are diſappointed, they<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135180:20"/>generally expect a happy man ſhould be deſcribed at the rate that <hi>Aſaph</hi> characters a wicked one;<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.12.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> that he is one that proſpers in the world, has riches in poſſeſſion, and can even do what he liſt; who is in no peril of death, but is always luſty and ſtrong; who comes into no misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune like other folk, neither is plagued like other men.<note place="margin">Verſ. 4, 5.</note> Who hath his belly full of treaſure, children at his deſire, and leaves the reſt of his ſubſtance to his babes.<note place="margin">Pſ. 17.14, 85.</note> And yet the very men but now deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, notwithſtanding their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, are the moſt unhappy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable men upon earth; for they are but a company of ungodly wicked wretches, all this while, men abhor'd by God, and whoſe condition and company is avoided and prayed againſt by good men.<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135180:21"/>But now <hi>Aſaph</hi> (who was a man of a clean heart and innocent hands, one whom God loved; who had no leſs than God for the ſtrength of his heart and his portion for ever; and therefore one whom we may juſtly conclude happy. For certainly of all men happy is he who is in ſuch a caſe, yea hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is the man who hath the Lord for his God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.15.</note> This holy, this happy Prophet, I ſay, gives this account of his condition. All the day long have I been plagued, and chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every morning.<note place="margin">Pſ.
73.14.</note> Nay he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates this to be the condition of all Gods children too, as well as of himſelf; and that if he ſhould ſay otherwiſe, he ſhould condemn the whole generation of his Heavenly Fathers houſhold.<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> And therefore they who are the moſt happy of all men, have the greateſt reaſon to<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135180:21"/>rejoice always in the Lord, who is the gracious beſtower of this their happineſs, yea and again I ſay to rejoice. Let us a while caſt our eyes upon ſome few afflictions which the world is apt to eſteem the moſt deplorable of miſeries, and ſee how a good Chriſtian can live above the ſadneſs of them all, and in the words of <hi>Samſon</hi>'s rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, draw forth meat out of the eater; and out of the ſtrong and the bitter, to derive inexpreſſible ſweetneſs.<note place="margin">Judg. 14.14.</note> Let but a worldly man, one of the ſons of <hi>Mammon,</hi> loſe his Eſtate, let him any way be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to want and beggery, and you'l ſee his content and joy as ſoon departed as his money; he's ſo far from having a cheerful heart or merry countenance, that he ſcarce hath the look or the ſoul of a man left him; his heart<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135180:22"/>is dead within him, and he's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like a ſtone, utterly inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and incapable of all comfort, not a word comes out of his mouth but undone, undone, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd, and for ever miſerable; all which argue the height of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolateneſs and deſpair. And let a man attempt to appeaſe his paſſion and ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of his ſorrow, and he preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys in a foaming rage, and in a language not unlike that of <hi>Micah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 18.24</note> My Gold, my God, all that I eſteem precious, is raviſhed from me and carried away, and what have I more? and then, why do you ask me what I ail, or perſwade me to be comforted? But now an obedient, humble, faithful, good Chriſtian, who hath learned in whatſoever eſtate he is, therewith to be content, he knows both how<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135180:22"/>to be abaſed, as well as how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound; every where, and in all things he is inſtructed, both to be full and to be hungry, both to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and ſuffer need, to uſe the words of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil.
4.11,12.</note> He looks upon poverty when 'tis ſent from God, (and when that is, we ſhall ſee by and by) as no ſuch frightful ſad condition; he can receive it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tears, entertain it without grudging, nay give it a hearty cheerful welcome. For having the ſame heart, he may very well be allowed to uſe the language of St. <hi>Paul</hi> whenſoever he is in his eſtate;
<hi>In all things I will approve my ſelf to God in much patience, in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes.</hi> Though the meanneſs I am redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to, makes me lookt upon as ſorrowful; yet in God can I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rejoice; and though I am<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135180:23"/>poor and have nothing, yet can I by the benefit of my good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and heavenly inſtruction, make many rich; and by the contentment of my mind, and the ſatisfaction I receive in the inner man, my ſelf poſſeſs all things.<note place="margin">2 Cor.
6.4,10. Verſ. 11.</note> Though I am reduced by Gods wiſe Providence to mean raiment, thin diet, and hard lodging; yet I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that a bare morſel of bread and a cup of water, was thought by the Father of the Faithful a treatment not unbecoming the glorious Angels themſelves to be invited to, when they vouchſafed to converſe amongſt mortals.<note place="margin">Gen. 18.3,4,5.</note> And certainly Gods bleſſing can ſtill make bare bread and clear water comfort their hearts for whom his Providence hath provided no more plentiful proviſion; he can make it not only keep them alive,<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135180:23"/>but in health too. Nay, with this can he preſerve them fat, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and cheerful alſo. I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive as much warmth by Gods bleſſing from a coarſe coat, and ſleep as ſweetly upon a hard bed, when God in his wiſdom allows me no better, as they who are moſt gorgeouſly apparelled, fare deliciouſly every day, and lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their beds of Ivory, and ſtretch themſelves upon their couches, and are lull'd to ſleep with a conſort of muſick.<note place="margin">Amos. 6.4,5.</note> Nay, ſhould my graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Father think fit to bring me yet lower, and not vouchſafe me ſo much as one garment of my own to clothe me, not one morſel of bread to feed me, nor the leaſt cottage of my own to harbor and reſt my weary decaying body; however I am not hitherto made comfortleſs, but have great reaſon<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135180:24"/>to ſay, Whil'ſt I live will I praiſe the Lord; yea, as long as I have any being will I ſing praiſe unto my God, who though he hath ſtript me of many uſeful outward accommodations, yet hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to me this never-failing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that he ſtill vouchſafes me his mercy to pray to, his promiſes to truſt in, and his good Providence to relye upon, which he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd me ſhall preſerve and provide for me, as he knows will be moſt for my advantage. And being thus brought by God himſelf to be one of his family, to live in a more eſpecial manner by the pure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of his Providence; To be fed out of his ſtore-houſe, and to be cloathed out of his Wardrobe, and take my reſt where he ſhall provide me a lodging; Certainly he who hath ſo bountiful, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate,<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135180:24"/>and ſo powerful a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, can't chuſe but be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accommodated and comforted during the whole diſcharge of his faithful ſervice. And therefore why ſhould I take thought, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vex my ſelf about what I ſhould eat, and what I ſhould drink, and wherewithal I ſhall be clothed, when I very well know that the God whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve, liberally provides all theſe for the lillies of the field, and the fowl of the air, without the leaſt of their care and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.<note place="margin">Math. 6.25,26.</note> Nay, the Holy Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms me, that the Son of his love, in whom the Father was always well pleaſed, was little better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for; he had neither houſe, nor land, nor revenues to furniſh him with a ſubſiſtence in the days of his fleſh, but lived all along for<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135180:25"/>above thirty years, eſpecially the three laſt of them, purely upon Gods Providence, and good mens charity. Though he hath often created food for his followers, yet he hath been ſometimes fain to beg it for himſelf; and for all that, never harbour'd the leaſt repining or diſſatisfaction at the meanneſs of his quality or entertainment. And moſt of thoſe renowned He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes (both before and after our Saviours Incarnation) men ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their Piety in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral generations, that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful wicked world was not worthy of their continuance in it, trod the very ſame ſteps: <hi>They wander'd about in ſheepskins, and goatskins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.17.</note> And yet all theſe by their faith in God, by their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon his Providence, by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135180:25"/>their thankfulneſs for his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their obedience to his will, <hi>obtained a good report;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 39.</note> very highly favour'd by God, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily reputed of amongſt men, their names and their vertues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. And now if to compleat the ſcene of my Poverty, it ſhould pleaſe God to bring me to ſuch a paſs, that neither my own endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, nor mens charity, nor any extraordinary diſpenſation, ſhould help me with bread to eat, nor clothes to put on (which hardly yet ever came to paſs); however it ſhould never come to paſs, but that the Lord ſhould be my God, him only would I ſerve, and on him alone would I place all my joy. And I ſhould think I had great reaſon to do ſo, if upon no other account, yet for this, that<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135180:26"/>he would be pleaſed amongſt all the children of men to make choice of me to witneſs to the world, that man lives not by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God;<note place="margin">Mat. 4.4.</note> And in a word, I ſhould neither have bread nor fleſh to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain me withal, I ſhould notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have one ſort of meat to eat which the world knows not of, and can never take from me, and that is the refreſhment of a good conſcience; this would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me many a delicious meal when every thing elſe is wanting; and the joy that does ariſe from the conſideration and proſpect of a well-led life, will furniſh me with a perpetual Gaudie, which will do more than adminiſter health to my navil, and marrow to my bones;<note place="margin">Prov. 3.8.</note> being able to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135180:26"/>then a fainting ſpirit, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven and cheer a dejected Soul. This will make ones heart merry, and that will without further care or trouble give a continual feaſt.<note place="margin">Prov. 15.15.</note> And when after all this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing treatment, I ſhall find na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to decay, and no longer able to ſupport my fading-tabernacle of clay, I would in all humility and contentment of mind reſign up my ſoul into the hands of my gracious Father, breathing out my laſt breath in the accents of fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Elijah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>It is enough now, O Lord, take away my life, for I am not better than my fathers.</hi> And I would not doubt but that God would in pity to my extream want and unreliev'd hunger, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mercifully take my Soul into his boſom of bleſſedneſs, or elſe (were I as good a man, and as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135180:27"/>a perſon to Gods Church as <hi>Elijah</hi> was) would as miraculouſly provide me with food to ſuſtain my feeble fainting nature, as he did for that his diſtreſſed lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Prophet. But beſides this of Poverty, a good Chriſtian can bear up his heart, and lift up his head with joy, amidſt all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, pain and vexation of a long tormenting ſickneſs. Many people, 'tis true, are in this particular of Satans opinion; they think they could eaſily grapple with all the hardſhips of poverty, and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt miſchief this world can bring upon them, ſo long as they enjoy their health; but if once God ſtretches out his hand upon their bodies, and ſmites them with a ſore diſeaſe, they can then no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hold their integrity, their hearts repine, and their tongues
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135180:27"/>blaſpheme, and their whole life is nothing but a ſcene of quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and defying of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Skin for skin, and all that they have, they could be content to give for their life, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their health; but if once God puts forth his hand, and touches but their bone and their fleſh, they preſently ſet their mouths againſt Heaven, and let fly againſt God himſelf, and in this condition adventure to curſe him to his face.<note place="margin">Job 2.4,5.</note> But now a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian when he once finds that God hath laid a ſore diſeaſe upon his loins, and caſt him upon his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, he does in all humility quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit to his ſtroke, heartily implore his mercy, and patiently attend his pleaſure, and with a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful confidence commits his body
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135180:28"/>and his ſoul into the hands of his gracious Father. For this indeed is the never failing comfort and principal cordial of his afflicted heart, That 'tis the merciful Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of the Univerſe who brought this ſickneſs upon him; that the ſame good God makes the ſore, and binds it up, and that he hath wounded him whoſe hands make whole.<note place="margin">Job 5.18.</note> So that though by reaſon of the infirmity of his fleſh he may poſſibly expreſs his unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſad condition in the language of holy <hi>Job,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.3,4.</note>
               <hi>I am made to poſſeſs months of vanity, and weariſome nights are appointed to me: When I lie down, I ſay, when ſhall I ariſe and the night he gone? I am full of toſſings to and fro unto the dawning of the day.</hi> Nay though he may continue his complaint to God in the words of holy
<hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:135180:28"/>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note>
               <hi>O Lord, thine arrows ſtick faſt in me, and thy hands preſſeth me ſore; there is no ſoundneſs in my fleſh, neither is there any reſt in my bones, my wounds ſtink and are corrupt, I am bowed down greatly, I go mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the day long.</hi> Yet can he cheer up his heart, and refreſh his ſoul with the comfortable lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the ſame holy Prophet, ſaying,<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, all my deſire is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and my groaning is not hid from thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note>
               <hi>And in thee do I hope, for thou wilt hear, O Lord my God.</hi> Nay, ſhould the ſame God bring him ſo low that he might truly ſay, <hi>The ſorrows of death compaſs me about, and the pains of hell get hold upon me:</hi> However he would have cauſe to ſay ſtill with the ſame <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
1.2,3.</note> 
               <hi>I will love the Lord my strength, and I will call upon the Lord, who</hi> (though he hath<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135180:29"/>humbled me to the very duſt of death, yet) <hi>is he ſtill worthy to be praiſed.</hi> And herein will appear how worthy God is of praiſe, even when he does afflict his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in this ſad manner, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how juſt cauſe ſuch an one hath even then to rejoice in the God that ſmites him; Becauſe as the ſame
<hi>David</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>Though I walk through the valley of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, I will fear none evil, for thou art with me; thy rod and thy ſtaff comfort me.</hi> 'Tis the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and aſſurance of Gods preſence with them in their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that bears up their hearts, and comforts the ſouls of Gods ſervants in the moſt diſmal cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, enabling them to rejoice in the worſt of tribulations. And yet 'tis not bare being with them, but the love and kindneſs he diſcovers<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135180:29"/>to them, that makes them thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied and joyful. He makes his very rod comfort them as well as his ſtaff. Ordinary rods indeed are dry inſipid things, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to give blows, and create a ſmart; but Gods rod hath a Prerogative beyond all others, in that, like <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod,<note place="margin">Numb.
17.8.</note> laid up by Gods appointment in the Ark, it blooms, bloſſoms, ſuch as by their ſweetneſs refreſh the ſpirits; and yields almonds, a fruit that delights and comforts the Soul. Nay, when the ſtrokes of his rod ſeem moſt to weaken and ſtrike them to the ground, then does God put his ſtaff into their hands, and that bears them up, and keeps them from falling; and therefore both together can't chuſe but afford an inexpreſſible comfort to thoſe good ſouls that<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135180:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>are exercis'd thereby. And 'tis for the continual ſupply of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and the frequent refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this cordial, that a devout ſoul is rais'd to ſuch a degree of ſatisfaction and exultation amidſt the very agonies of death, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables her in that dire conflict tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly to cry out in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of afflicted <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 3.15,16.</note> 
               <hi>Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him. He alſo ſhall be my Salvation.</hi> And 'tis the ſame overflowing comfort that God vouchſafes a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that bears up his heart, and lifts up his head above all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces and calumnies that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ungrateful world throws up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. He knows a bleſſing goes along with him when men revile him, and perſecute him, and ſay all manner of evil againſt him falſely upon account of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135180:30"/>adhering to Chriſt and his Goſpel. And 'tis the aſſurance of this, that enables him to rejoice and be exceeding glad; anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our Saviours encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that particular affliction.<note place="margin">Math. 8.11,12.</note> Nay 'tis the ſame merciful God that ſupplys them with an exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant joy in recompence for all the unkindneſs they meet with at the hands of cruel relations and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful friends. <hi>David</hi> indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us,<note place="margin">Pſ. 27.13.</note> 
               <hi>That he had certainly fainted but that he believed to ſee the goodneſs of the Lord in the land of the living.</hi> And herein God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt his goodneſs to him, that <hi>when his father and his mother for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him, the Lord took him up.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ.
10.</note> And 'twas his receiving this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable comfortable mercy that made him reſolutely wait on the Lord, and be of good courage,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135180:31"/>knowing that he did and would ſtrengthen his heart.<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> Nay further, when he was brought to that ſad condition that his own familiar friend in whom he truſted, who alſo eat of his bread, had lift up his heel againſt him, an affliction that of all others ſeems to go neareſt to his heart, and which he was leaſt able to bear:
<hi>For if it had been an enemy that reproached him, then he could have born it;</hi> by whom he implies the perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a friend to be almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable.<note place="margin">Pſ. 55.12.</note> And yet even in the worſt of miſeries was he not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of a ſatisfactory comfort:
<hi>Thou, O Lord,</hi> ſays he, <hi>upholdeſt me in my integrity, and ſetteſt me before thy face for ever.</hi> And for this reaſon ſays he,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.9,12,13.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to everlaſting. Amen and Amen.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:135180:31"/>We have the cleareſt inſtance of what was but now delivered, in the perſon and practiſe of holy <hi>Job,</hi> a man afflicted beyond compare, and yet ſatisfied and joyful beyond all example. Let us but obſerve how of the richeſt man of the Eaſt, he was in a few hours redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be one of the pooreſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon earth. His ſervants we find ſlain, and his cattel carried away by the hands of thieves and murderers; his ſheep and his ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds were conſumed by fire from heaven; his ſons and his daughters kill'd by the fall of the houſe blown down upon their heads: And yet all the diſcontent that <hi>Job</hi> expreſſes at theſe ſad tidings, was only his worſhipping and praiſing God, ſo ſays the Text,<note place="margin">Job 1.20,21,22.</note>
               <hi>Then Job aroſe and rent his mantle, and ſhaved his head, and fell down upon<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135180:32"/>the ground and worſhipped, and ſaid, Naked came I out of my mothers womb, and naked ſhall I return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, when God allowed the Devil to execute ſo much of his malice upon him as to ſmite his body with ſore boils from the ſoal of his foot to his crown; whereby we may eaſily gueſs that the noiſomeneſs and the pain made his life a burden to himſelf and his friends; and when the wife of his boſom had perſwaded him to end his days with Blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, at once as 'twere to defie and revenge himſelf upon the Author of his Miſery; He was ſo far from doing ſo, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking her for her wicked advice, <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt</hi> (ſays he<note place="margin">Job
2.9,10.</note>) <hi>as one of<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135180:32"/>the fooliſh women ſpeaketh.</hi> He there acquaints her with his content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſatisfaction in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent povertous painful condition; <hi>What? ſhall we receive good at the hand of God</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and ſhall we not receive evil?</hi> 'Tis unreaſonable we ſhould covet the one, and not accept the other, when they both come from the ſame gracious hand.</p>
            <p>Nay, when his three friends had made an appointment together to come to mourn with him and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, as we are told,<note place="margin">Job
2.11.</note> and yet inſtead of doing ſo, made it their great buſineſs to reproach him, and accuſe him as ſome notorious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or vile Hypocrite; for ſo ſays <hi>Eliphaz</hi> in the name of the reſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 47.</note> 
               <hi>Remember, I pray thee, whoever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed being innocent, or where were the righteous cut off?</hi> All the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<hi>Job</hi> returns to their unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135180:33"/>character, calumny, is in that meek but ſmart reply,<note place="margin">Job
6.14,15.</note> 
               <hi>To him that is afflicted, pity ſhould be ſhewed from his friend: How forcibly are right words? but what doth your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reprove?</hi> Endeavouring all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in his whole diſpute with them, at once to clear Gods Juſtice, and to vindicate his own Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and upon the whole to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his matchleſs Patience, his high content, and uninterrupted joy, through the whole ſcene of his diſmal wretched condition; the main foundation you ſee of <hi>Job</hi>'s comfort in his affliction, was his aſſurance that his poverty and ſickneſs came from Gods own hand. <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſays he, <hi>hath taken away.</hi> His own wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, riot, or idleneſs had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted nothing to it: But he ſaw
'twas purely the Lords doing, and<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135180:33"/>that was the reaſon that he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his mouth.</p>
            <p>And indeed, whenſoever a good Chriſtian upon the impartial ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his heart, can find that 'twas neither his gluttony, nor his drunkenneſs, neither his idleneſs, extortion, defrauding, over-reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; his worldly-mindedneſs, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, or unthankfulneſs, that have provoked God to withhold his bleſſing from him in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his affairs, ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his honeſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous endeavours, his diligence in his calling, his devotion to God, his intire dependance upon him for ſucceſs, it ſtill pleaſes the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty on high to leſſen his Eſtate, and by variety of ſad Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to bring him to beggery; He hath now the juſteſt cauſe of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in his Poverty that can be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135180:34"/>deſired. He may pronounce with truth in the language of old <hi>Eli,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> And he may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelf (and rejoice in the very thought of it) that
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.5.</note>
               <hi>gracious is the Lord and righteous, yea our God is merciful.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13,14.</note>
               <hi>And that as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pitieth his children, ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him; he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our frame, he remembers that we are but duſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewiſe when a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian obſerves his ſickneſs to come from God, his diſeaſe ariſing from no act of intemperance or luxury, from no greedy inceſſant proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his buſineſs, nor from any bold preſuming upon his ſtrength, or ſlighting the ſeverities of wind, air and weather, much leſs from the perpetual following his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and his eager addictedneſs to<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135180:34"/>his ſport; He may then with an humble confidence repoſe himſelf upon Gods goodneſs for eaſe and cure; not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that God will ſtrengthen him upon his bed of languiſhing, <hi>&amp; will make all his bed in his ſickneſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.3.</note> enable him with ſtrength to go thorough with his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per if it be great; or elſe leſſen the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe if he be too weak to bear it at its heighth. And whereas others in their fits of ſickneſs, lie like ſo many wild bulls in a net raving and tumbling in a moſt impatient manner, <hi>and refuſe to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, becauſe they are full of the fury of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 41.20</note> An humble good Chriſtian does with all quietneſs reſign up himſelf to his heavenly Phyſicians ordering, looking upon Gods dealing with him in the whole courſe of his ſickneſs, as a procedure full of mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſuch as aims at nothing but the Patients health and ſoundneſs; deſigned ſo to make him whole, that he ſins no more. And therefore though Gods handling him be never ſo irkſome to fleſh and blood, yet does he look upon it, and rejoice in it, as a neceſſary method for<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135180:35"/>the curing the tumors and ulcers of his diſeaſed ſoul. And this ſtrengthens his feeble knees, and enables him to lift up the hands that hang down, and to praiſe God even when he hath brought him to the brink of the grave. <hi>For though no chaſtiſement at the preſent ſeems to be joyous but grievous;</hi> yet 'tis worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that 'tis only ſaid it ſeems ſo, and not that it is ſo, for it hath indeed an inconceivable joy wrapt and coucht in it, for them that are exerciſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, though there are few eyes ſo pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that can diſcern it. Yea, affliction affords an infinite ſatisfaction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to them that are ſo far exerciſed thereby, that they ſeem (like wreſtlers in the <hi>Olympick</hi> Games) quite ſtript by, and for their encountering with it; for ſo the Original ſignifies, reduced to that condition that have not clothes to cover their nakedneſs, nor an houſe to hide their head in. And this is the chief cauſe that they faint not in the worſt of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations; becauſe though their <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man doth periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day,</hi> to uſe St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s words.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:135180:35"/>Now the comforts of a Soul are really ſo great, that they are above all deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, none being able ſufficiently to know them but he that hath them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us to underſtand ſomething of them (by which I ſhall leave you to gueſs at their inexpreſſible excellency and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) in that account he gives of himſelf to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where he ſays,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That though he was troubled out of meaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſtrength, inſomuch that he deſpaired even of life;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> Yet could he in that hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and almoſt helpleſs condition pour out his heart to God in that joyful Thankſgiving,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note>
               <hi>Bleſſed be God even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies, &amp; the God of all comforts, who comforteth us in all our tribulation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note>
               <hi>For as the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in us ſo our conſolation alſo aboundeth by Chriſt.</hi> And hence it was that he that became capable of all this comfort, <hi>viz.</hi> for the conſideration of his well-led-life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance whereof muſt needs refreſh not only him but all ſuch as he was;
<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note>
               <hi>For our rejoicing is this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135180:36"/>godly ſincerity, by the grace of God, we have had our converſation in this world; keeping a conſcience void of offence both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Gods and towards all men.</hi> He that does this, hath juſt cauſe (whatſoever his condition in this world may happen to be)
<hi>to rejoice in the Lord always, &amp; again I ſay to rejoice.</hi> Being able to defie his laſt grim enemy in that Triumph of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> 
               <hi>O death, where is thy ſting! O grave, where is thy victory!</hi> And in that great day of darkneſs to give
<hi>thanks to God who giveth us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude all in the following words, <hi>Therefore my beloved Brethren be ye ſtedfaſt, unmovable in this thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, praiſing and rejoicing in him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways abounding in this work of the Lord; foraſmuch as you know that your labour, yea and your leiſure too, your ſuffering and your joy, are not in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which God, the only beſtower of all true comfort and conſolation be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all Honour and Glory, Might, Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, Praiſe and Thankſgiving, <hi>in Saecula.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135180:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
